A Guide to the Personal Papers of Nan Netherton, 1946-2000
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Personal Papers of Nan Netherton, 1946-2000
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 76
5 boxes.
Netherton, Nan
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Nan Netherton in August 1998.
Biographical Information
Anne "Nan" Netherton (1926-2003) was a prominent historian and researcher of both Arlington County and all of Northern Virginia. Netherton and her husband Ross co-wrote a book on Arlington County titled Arlington County in Virginia: A Pictorial History in 1987. Born in Illinois, Netherton moved to Northern Virginia in 1950 after working on the Manhattan Project during World War II and found that the area, while in a period of transition from rural to suburban, was historically interesting and important. She worked for Fairfax County as a staff member for the Office of Comprehensive Planning and compiled an 800-page history of the county for the U.S. Bicentennial celebrations in 1976. The Nethertons published many works on the history and development of Northern Virginia, especially in Fairfax County, where they resided, including Memories of Beautiful Burke, Virginia (1988), Fairfax County, Virginia: A History (1978), and Reston: A New Town in the Old Dominion (1989). Additionally, Nan volunteered for the Fairfax Historic Landmarks Commission, was elected president of the Northern Virginia Association for History in 1988, and received the Association's Joseph Harsh Award for her work in historic preservation of local history in 2000.
Scope and Content
The personal papers in this collection were generated by Nan Netherton. The collection is approximately 4.5 linear feet and dates from 1946 to 2000 with the bulk of dates ranging from the mid-1970s to the mid-1980s. Much of the material in this collection is generated from her research on Theodore Roosevelt Island and economic, residential, and physical development of Arlington. Many materials in this collection are photocopies of articles and primary sources on her research subjects. There are scattered photographs, both copies of originals in other repositories and uncredited photographs.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series. Series 1 is research from Netherton's book on Theodore Roosevelt Island. Any folders in this series in quotes ("") are original folder titles created by Netherton. In this series, portions of folder titles in brackets ([]) have been added by the archivist for clarification. Series 2 contains historical notes and research conducted by Netherton; Series 3 contains news clippings and other information about economic and residential development in Arlington County. The archivist has created the folder titles for these two series. Folders containing photographs have an asterisk [*] after the file name. Folders with oversized materials have a double asterisk [**] to denote where material was removed and separation sheets added.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
The records of other Arlington historical researchers and authors can be found in RG 23, the Personal Papers of Eleanor Templeman, RG 91, Papers of Dorothea Abbott, RG 103, Freeman's Village and Reconstruction Collection, and RG 354, Papers of C. B. Rose.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Arlington County (Va.); History -- Research.; Theodore Roosevelt Island (Washington, D.C.); Arlington County (Va.); Arlington (Va.)
Contents List
- Research on Theodore Roosevelt Island
  - Theodore Roosevelt Island, Other T. Roosevelt Park Brochures, 1979-1980, 1982-1983, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Theodore Roosevelt Island Speeches, 1988, n.d. (Box 1)
  - "Graphics" (1) Theodore Roosevelt Island Research, May 24, 1979 (Box 1)
  - "Graphics" (2) Theodore Roosevelt Island Research, May 24, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Theodore Roosevelt Island Research Notes, n.d. (Box 1)
  - [Citations (1)], n.d. (Box 1)
  - [Citations (2)], n.d. (Box 1)
  - [Citations (3)], n.d. (Box 2)
  - [Citations (4)], n.d. (Box 2)
  - [Citations (5)], n.d. (Box 2)
  - "Theodore Roosevelt Island" Correspondence and Contact, 1979-1984 (Box 2)
  - "Theodore Roosevelt Island" Correspondence and Contact, 1987, n.d. (Box 2)
  - "Theodore Roosevelt Island" Brochures, Photographs, Theodore Roosevelt Association, 1983-1984 * (Box 2)
  - "Theodore Roosevelt References," 1980-1983 (Box 2)
  - "Theodore Roosevelt Speech," 1985 (Box 2)
  - "Preliminary Draft with Revised Draft Corrections," March 1980 (Box 2)
  - "Roosevelt Island Graphics," 1978, 1984 (Box 3)
  - "Theodore Roosevelt Island" Illustrations, 1980-1983, n.d.* (Box 3)
  - "Acknowledgements - Theodore Roosevelt Island," June 5, 1979 (Box 3)
  - "Theodore Roosevelt Island Expenses and Receipt" Brochure, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Theodore Roosevelt Association Journals, 1980-1985 (Box 3)
  - Theodore Roosevelt Association Journals, 1980-1983 (Box 3)
  - "F. Gutheim - The Federal City: Plans and Realities," 1976 (Box 3)
  - "Historic American Buildings Survey Catalog: District of Columbia," 1968 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous and Roosevelt Renaissance, 1978-1979, 1982-1984, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Theodore Roosevelt Publications, 1958, 1979, 1983, 1984 (Box 3)
  - "Arlington - Black History," 1939, 1974, 1983-1986, n.d.** (Box 3)
- Historic Files on Arlington County
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1967-2000 ** (Box 4)
  - Arlington Hospital Pictorials, 1982-1985 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Arlington Historical Society newsletters, 1984-1985, 1991-1999 (Box 4)
  - Brochures, 1973-1988, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Arlington County historical research, n.d. (Box 4)
  - United States Capitol Historical Society, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Library Programs, 1984, 1986, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Arlington National Cemetery Historical Society Articles of Incorporation, n.d. (Box 4)
  - District of Columbia Boundary Bicentennial Commemoration Ceremony Program, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Oral History Association Newsletter, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Conference Materials, 1983-1985, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 1962, 1981, n.d.* (Box 4)
  - Review of The Cartography of Northern Virginia, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Centennial Celebration Program, September 1946 (Box 4)
- Development in Arlington County
  - Demographic Pamphlets, 1983, 1986, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1981, 1983, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Vietnamese Language Newspaper, 1986 ** (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Maps and Brochures, 1964, 1984, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Washington Metropolitan Area Transportation Authority Maps and Brochures, 1982 ** (Box 4)
  - Arlington County Parks and Recreation, 1964, 1984, n.d.** (Box 4)
  - "Arlington's Neighborhood Conservation Program" Guide, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Arlington County, Virginia Profile Pamphlet, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Arlington County Hospital Brochures, 1983, 1986, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Arlington County Residential Development Information, 1983, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Washington, D.C., Airports - Washington National adn Washington-Dulles International Airport Guide, 1985, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Ballston, 1984-1986 (Box 5)
  - The Arlington Committee of 100, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Chamber of Commerce Speech by Chuck Delashmutt, August 13, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Arlington County Schools Newspaper Clippings, 1955, 1974, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - "Parkington: Shopping Center Design" Plans, 1952 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Arlington County Land Development, 1982, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1982, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Transportation, 1967, 1983, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Northern Virginia Chapter of the Virginia Society of Ornithology Membership Application, October 5, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Correspondence, Rosslyn, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Washington-Lee High School Student Handbook, 1986-1987 ** (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Clarendon, 1972, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Arlington County Road Tests for Asphalt and Concrete, 1923 (Box 5)
  - Resume of Larry J. Brown, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Photocopied Photographs, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Photographs and Negatives, 1921, 1930, n.d.* (Box 5)